Let’s say you’re trying to
find some solid information
about a serious health
problem that concerns you,
like high blood pressure,
or diabetes.
Yet, everywhere you look,
someone’s trying to sell you
something like vitamins,
yoga mats, blenders, drugs.
Well, breathe a
sigh of relief
because all we bring
you are the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the effect
yoga may or may not have
on a wide variety of conditions,
and yes, I do a little myth-
busting in both directions.
The practice of yoga for health
has become popular
in the United States and worldwide.
A 2016 survey estimated
that 36 million Americans
may be involved in yoga
to varying degrees.
Though the origins of yoga
go back thousands of years,
it was only introduced in the
United States about a century ago.
What are the risks
and the benefits?
Yoga users tend to report
having a better health status,
but that doesn't necessarily
mean yoga was the cause.
For example, yoga practitioners
were more likely to be normal weight
rather than obese, and that alone
could give you better health.
Of course, if the yoga was
responsible for the weight loss,
then that would certainly
be to yoga's credit,
but yoga users are also more
likely to be white, female, young,
and college educated ---
all of which are independently
associated with better health status.
The same thing with higher
socioeconomic status.
Yoga practitioners also tend
to exhibit other positive
health behaviors,
specifically more regular
physical activity in general
and a vegetarian diet.
And the more yoga
people practiced, the
more likely they were
to cut out meat, and to eat more
and more fruits and vegetables.
For every additional day
per week of yoga practice,
the odds of being vegetarian
increased 20%.
About 1 in 3 yoga teachers surveyed
in the UK follow a plant-based diet,
much higher than
the general population.
So when you're doing
a study like this,
comparing the cardiovascular
health of yoga practitioners
to runners, to sedentary individuals,
you can see how difficult it would be
to tease out the effects of yoga,
when significantly more yogis
reported refraining from eating meat
compared to the other two groups.
It's like when I was reading about
the role of yoga in the prevention
and management of various
cardiovascular diseases.
I was so excited to read
that yoga could significantly
reduce cholesterol levels.
After all, heart disease is
the #1 killer of men and women.
And when I looked up those
studies, I got really excited.
Reversal of coronary
atherosclerosis with yoga?
I thought the only
lifestyle intervention
that could reliably do that was
a whole food plant-based diet.
Well, what do you think the
Yoga Lifestyle Intervention was?
A diet packed so full
of whole plant foods---
fruits, vegetables, whole
grains, beans and nuts---
they were getting about
50 grams of fiber a day.
No wonder they got
heart disease reversal.
But what role, if any, did
the yoga itself actually play?
Now, if yoga gets you
to adopt a better lifestyle---
stop smoking, eat healthier---
great.
Whatever gets people to
take better care of themselves.
If your tinfoil hat tells you
Martians want you
to skip the doughnuts,
I'm all in favor.
Whatever it takes.
But if we are to tease out
whether practicing yoga
has any special benefits
in and of itself,
we really need to look
at interventional studies,
randomized controlled trials
that go beyond just associations
and correlations and can instead
prove cause-and-effect.
For example, when we find yoga
users have better health status
and are less likely to be obese,
that could be reverse causation,
meaning instead of yoga
leading to better health
and a normal weight,
maybe being in better health,
not being obese,
is leading to more yoga.
Same with the flipside.
When you read that yoga
practitioners are more likely
to have mental health conditions
(depression, anxiety),
musculoskeletal conditions (like
arthritis, gout, lupus, fibromyalgia,
joint pain, sprains, and asthma),
yeah, maybe yoga
could be contributing
to some of those conditions
like muscle sprain.
But for most of these
it's probably reverse causation:
people with diseases seeking help.
Are they getting it?
The only way to know for sure
is to put it to the test
which we'll explore next.
Yoga is practiced
by millions of Americans
and is often recommended
as therapy
for a variety of medical conditions,
but does it work and for what?
In my last video, I talked about how
yoga practitioners tend to report
better health status, but they
also tend to be wealthier,
and confounding factors like that
make it hard to draw claims
about yoga efficacy.
For example, when population
studies have taken factors
like education or income into account,
the yoga effects often evaporate.
You can't really tell if something
is good or bad
until you put it to the test.
Unfortunately, only about
a quarter of the published studies
examining the effects yoga on
health or well-being outcomes
were randomized controlled trials,
and of those, half compared yoga
to basically just doing nothing.
In that case if you find benefit,
you don't know if it's the yoga itself
or whether any kind of exercise
would have achieved
the same or even better effect.
Now look, any kind of physical activity
is good, but is there more
to yoga than exercise?
For example, any kind of exercise,
whether low intensity, such as yoga,
or high intensity, such as aerobics,
may help with menstrual pain,
compared to not doing anything.
In studies on alcoholics, aerobic
exercise alleviated depression
and anxiety symptoms
more than yoga,
presumably just because
of the greater exercise intensity.
Typical yoga is
probably best described
as a light-intensity physical
activity. For example,
here's the metabolic equivalents
of some typical yoga poses.
They average maybe 2 or 3.
Compare that to walking at
a typical speed, which is about 3.
So, in general, walking burns
about as many calories as yoga,
and brisk walking would
burn even more.
There's all sorts of crazy claims
about how so-called "hot yoga"
expends up to like
1000 calories, but no,
you burn about the same
calories at room temperature,
so 90 minutes would just
be more like 300 calories.
But isn't yoga so much more
than just a workout?
Let's see how the data pan out.
Multiple sclerosis, for example.
We know that exercise can be
beneficial in many health conditions,
including neurological disorders.
And it may not be surprising that
yoga, which involves a series
of poses, postures, movements,
and breathing patterns
that could improve balance,
muscle strength, and flexibility,
should be found
beneficial to patients
with, say, multiple sclerosis.
Let's see if that's actually true.
No benefit for overall quality of life,
or physical quality of life,
or psychological quality of life.
Also, no benefit for sexual function
or cognitive function,
and this was all comparing
yoga to doing nothing.
A similar failure to find much
improvement in quality of life
for people living with chronic
diseases in general was noted
with only 1 in 7 trials finding
a clinically significant benefit.
Researchers did find yoga
helped fatigue in patients with MS,
but not any better than
regular exercise.
Same with chronic low back pain.
Yoga might decrease pain
and improve function compared
to not really doing anything,
but had the same effect
on pain and disability
as any other exercise
or physical therapy.
So if you like yoga
and want to make that
your exercise of choice, great,
but it doesn't appear to have
any unique benefits for back pain.
Same with insomnia.
Yoga works compared to nothing,
but not to physically active controls.
And for cancer patients --
mostly breast cancer patients --
walking was found to be
more effective than yoga
at improving sleep.
For markers of systemic inflammation
in breast cancer survivors,
6 months of yoga had a similar effect
as 6 months of non-yoga exercise.
Same with cancer-related fatigue
and quality of life for women
with breast cancer:
better than nothing,
but no better than other
types of physical activity.
Finally, for breast cancer survivors,
the effectiveness
of yoga interventions
in breast cancer-related
lymphedema,
an abnormal accumulation
of fluid for which
there's no effective treatment,
and adding yoga
does not seem to help.
There are some conditions
for which yoga really does
appear to pull ahead
of the pack though,
for example, chronic
nonspecific neck pain.
Based on 10 randomized
controlled trials,
not only was yoga
better for neck pain
than control groups in general,
which included doing nothing,
yoga also seemed to beat out active
controls, other types of exercises.
The authors tentatively conclude that
yoga can relieve neck pain intensity,
improve pain-related disability,
increase range of motion,
improve quality of life, and boost
mood among neck pain sufferers.
Finally today,
what happens when real yoga
is compared to sham yoga?
Yoga is an ancient mind-body
discipline which originated in India
thousands of years ago,
and that's where most yoga
studies are done to this day.
This has raised concerns
that national pride
might incline Indian researchers
to quietly shelve any negative results
and just publish studies
showing yoga works.
This fear is not without precedent.
For example, research conducted in
China, Japan, Hong Kong, and Taiwan
was found to be uniformly
favorable to acupuncture;
all trials, without exception,
were positive.
Now, one possible explanation
for this finding
is that acupuncture is just
more effective in countries
where it is traditionally practiced,
but it's a little suspicious.
So, are Indian yoga trials
more likely to be positive
than those from other countries?
They looked at hundreds of
randomized controlled trials of yoga,
both done in India and
done in other countries,
and trials on yoga conducted in India
had about 25 times the odds
of reaching positive conclusions
as those conducted elsewhere.
Again, yes, yoga might be more
effective in India than elsewhere,
but it is a little suspicious.
So, for example, if you're interested
in whether yoga is helpful
for treating headaches,
and you read that yoga
appears to be helpful
for those suffering from
tension-type headaches,
but then you find out nearly
all such studies were
conducted in India,
what do you do
with that information?
Also, notably, none
of the control groups
had any sort of exercise component,
though this may be less critical
for tension headaches, since
neither aerobic exercise training...
nor strength training
appears to help them.
So if we're to believe
the Indian study conclusions,
yoga may indeed help
with tension headaches,
but even they found
no effect for migraines.
What may help migraines,
though, is other types of exercise,
specifically aerobic exercise,
decreasing migraine pain intensity,
frequency, and duration,
at least in the short-term.
What about the benefits
of yoga practice
compared to physical exercise
in the management
of type 2 diabetes?
A significant reduction
in both short-term and
longer-term blood sugar control
was noted in the yoga groups
compared to other
exercise control groups.
However, the findings may need
to be interpreted with caution,
since nearly half of the studies
didn't define and adhere to
a well-planned exercise regimen
in the control group.
Furthermore, an exercise intervention
comparable in intensity to yoga
was followed only in three
out of the eight studies included.
And, for what it's worth,
the majority of the studies,
6 out of 8, were from India.
When yoga was carefully
compared to sham yoga,
which consisted of chair exercises,
standing exercises,
and slow walking to match
the yoga session,
the relative yoga
benefits evaporated.
Both yoga and sham yoga
had identical effects
on blood sugar status.
Hence, further well-controlled
randomized trials are required
prior to drawing conclusions
about the benefits of yoga
in comparison to physical exercise
in patients with diabetes.
Similar tentative conclusions were
reached for yoga for osteoarthritis.
Put all the studies together
and yoga may indeed be effective
for improving pain, function,
and stiffness in individuals
with osteoarthritis of the knee,
compared not only
to doing nothing, but compared
to other kinds of exercise.
They had some issues with
the quality of some of the studies,
and so only a weak recommendation
for the use of yoga for osteoarthritis,
but hey, if you like yoga or if yoga
is the only kind of exercise
you're willing to do, then
it's probably better than nothing.
Finally, in this video,
let's look at the effects of yoga
compared to active and inactive
controls meaning like compared
to other exercise regimens
or just like doing nothing
on physical function and
health-related quality of life
in adults aged 60 and older.
Compared to doing nothing,
they found clear evidence
that yoga improves physical function
and psychological wellbeing
in older adults, so definitely
better than nothing.
What about compared
to other exercises?
Yoga pulled ahead for lower limb
strength and lower body flexibility,
but for improving balance,
mobility, and walking speed,
yoga appeared comparable.
Psychologically, yoga appeared
to beat out other exercises
for alleviating depression
in older adults,
but not anxiety or perceived
mental health in general.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books were
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of “How Not to Age”.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.